stimulus-based multiple choice questions
you either love them or you hate them
i'm kidding everybody hates them they're
confusing they take too long and they
are a source of endless ap exam season
anxiety but they don't have to be in
this video i'm going to help you
understand how to approach these
questions and if you follow my advice
you will almost certainly improve so if
you're ready to get them brain cows
milked but then let's get to it oh and
hey i'm steve heimler and i'm here to
help you get an a in your class and a
five on your exam in may but you can't
get a five on that exam without doing
fairly well on those multiple choice
questions which make up about forty
percent of your score so let's figure it
out and everything i'm about to say
applies to ap euro apus and ap world
first let's talk about the timing you'll
have 55 of these questions and you'll
have 55 minutes to complete them which
if you carry the 1 and multiply by the
sine wave is one minute per question now
i am going to make another video about
these next week and how to get faster
with them but for now all you need to
understand is this the people who make
these tests know how long you have for
this section and that's important to
remember because that means that they're
not expecting you to spend hours pouring
over these documents and coming to a
deep understanding about them you've got
to read them fairly quickly and just get
the gist and if that's what you're doing
and you feel like you're doing it wrong
you're not like that's all you have time
for second let's talk about order of
operations which is to say what is the
first second and third thing you should
do with every question first you need to
read the question i know you're going to
be tempted to read the stimulus first
but restrain thyself if you read the
question first then you know what you
need to look for in the stimulus and
that will save you time second read the
attribution this little line right here
is not a throwaway text it's going to
give you some really valuable
information including the time period
that you need to be thinking about and
the people and the entities involved in
the stimulus and third read the stimulus
and when you do read it quickly mark up
whatever you think might help you answer
the question that you've already read
now that you've read and interpreted the
stimulus it's time to answer the
question you'll have four possible
answers to choose from and those answers
will be one of three species you're
gonna have two obviously wrong answers
and the reason that they're wrong is
because they're in a different time
period than the question is asking about
which is most common or they're giving
you a different historical thinking
skill than the question is asking about
which is less common what i mean is if
the question asks you about how events
in the stimulus cause a change in
something then the obviously wrong
answer could indicate a continuity which
is to say you know not a change so
that's the first species of wrong answer
the second species is called a
distractor this is an answer that is
usually factually correct but ultimately
doesn't answer the question that they're
asking and last of all you have the
right answer so the first thing you need
to do is eliminate the two obviously
wrong answers and here's where i take a
moment for a parenthetical remark like i
know that it's easy for me to say
eliminate the obviously wrong answers
like i've been teaching these courses
for a long time and the obviously wrong
answers jump out to me immediately but
unless you have just flat out mastered
the content of this course what i say
are the obviously wrong answers are not
gonna be so obvious to you so the remedy
for that is twofold and they both have
to do with studying first let me
emphasize yet again that there is no
substitute for knowing the content of
this course get those vocabulary words
firmly stuffed in your brain folds and
that will go a long way second you need
to arrange those concepts in the time
periods of the course if you know what
vocabulary goes in what period then the
obviously wrong answers will become more
obvious because you'll know that they're
trying to trick you with the wrong time
period okay parenthesis ended now all
that is strategy and now i'm going to
give you a few tactical tips for the
multiple choice section in general first
answer all the questions blank circles
get no credit but if you fill in a
circle hey you know you got a 25 chance
of getting it right second don't change
your answer unless you are 100
sure that you put down the wrong answer
i know that's scary but just trust me
here go with your gut and that will
serve you better than overthinking it
plus you don't have time to overthink it
so you know listen to your gut it's the
transcontinental railroad well thanks
god third if you're not convinced of
what i just said then hear this you
don't have to do as well on these
questions as you think to score a five
now the percentages change every year
and of course there are three other
sections of the exam to factor in but in
general those students who score in the
mid 70s on the multiple choice are on
their way to a thigh and wider high
school world 75 isn't something to shout
from the rooftops but in ap exam world
oh baby you just won now if you want to
see me actually walk through multiple
choice questions for ap world and a push
then click right over here you can see
all these tips in action and see how i
think through them so i'll catch you
over there heimler out